William R. Mathews papers 1870-1980
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Public Service Files, 1926-1964, Series V:
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Initiative Petition, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Knoxville Electric Power and Water Board, 1935-1943 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Meeting Minutes, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Ordinance Acquisition Election, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Rates Comparisons, 1926-1947 (Box 9, Folder 11-13)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Reports: Burns and McDonnell Engineering Company, 1935-1944 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Reports: Duff and Phelps. 1944 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Reports: Finance Committee, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Resolutions: Dahlberg and Durand, 1941-1943 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Resolutions: Stranahan, Harris and Company, Inc., 1944 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Safford Utility Court Decision, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; San Antonio Utility Purchase, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Security and Exchange Commission, 1942-1946 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, Analysis from, 1936-1946 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, Annual Meeting Notice, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, Annual Reports, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, Annual Reports, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, Annual Reports, 1944-1946 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, Income Tax Returns, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, Pension Trust Plan, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Utilities Purchase, Mayor's Statement, undated (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Mid-Century Conference on Resources for the Future Steering Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 30-31)
  - Pima County Zoning, 1928-1952 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Pulitzer Prize Committee, 1954-1956 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - State School Funds, 1951-1956 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Sunshine Climate Club, 1951-1952 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Tucson School Bond Elections, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - United States Atomic Energy Commission, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Young Women's Christian Association; New Building Committee, 1950-1954 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Travel Files, 1937-1968, Series VI:
  This series documents Mr. Mathews' extensive international travels. The files include travel itineraries, photographs, field notebooks, dispatches and other writings and memorabilia. Arrangement is alphabetical.
  - Africa; 1961, 1961-1963 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Alaska, 1957-1962 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Antarctica; 1961, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 7-9)
  - Bikini; 1946, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - China; 1937, 1937-1945 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Dutch Indonesia; 1949, 1949-1956 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Europe; 1945-1947, 1945-1947 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Europe; 1951, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Germany; 1962, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Korea; Dulles Mission; 1950, 1950-1967 (Box 10, Folder 16-17)
  - Near East; 1962, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Orient; 1945, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
  - Pearl Harbor; Aboard U.S.S. Oriskany (CVA34), 1960 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - South America; 1955-1956, 1955-1963 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - South Viet Nam; 1966, 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Soviet Union; 1954, 1942-1957 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Venezuela; Meeting in Caracas, 1963, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1886--1980, Series VII:
  This series is divided into three subseries: General (1886-circa 1940), Albums (1928-1969) and Oversize (1943-1980). General includes military photographs that document U.S. Navy and Marine Corps training exercises and facilities, World War I personal and aerial photos, and images of William R. Mathews. Albums include photographs documenting Mr. Mathews' travels, meetings with notable individuals and leaders, as well as his military interests and public service activities. Of note are photographs documenting the signing of the Japanese surrender ending World War II and images of the Bikini Bomb Test from aboard the U.S.S. Appalachian. Oversize includes items from both the General and Albums subseries and also includes the family photographs of the Boyers and Mathews families.
  - General; 1886-circa 1940, Subseries 1:
    - Marine Corps Air Station; Physical Fitness Center, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Navy Training, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - World War I, Aerial Photos of Battle Areas, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - World War I; Photos Carried by Mathews, William R., undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Mathews and Boyers Family Photos, 1886-circa 1940 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Albums, 1928-1969, Subseries 2:
    - Japanese Military, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Military and International Leaders, 1928-1969 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Oversize, 1943-1980, Subseries 3:
    - Albums; International Travel, 1944-1968 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Albums; Marine Corps and Navy, 1943-1963 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
    - Albums; Professional and Public Service. 1947-1965 (Box 12, Folder 4-6)
    - Mathews, William R. undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - 4 framed photographs of Mathews and Boyers family, undated (Box 12a)
    - Framed certificate to Mrs. Betty Boyers; University of Arizona Health Sciences Center, 1980 (Box 12a)
- Scrapbooks, 1916-1968, Series VIII:
  This series is divided into three subseries: Military (1916-1968), Newspaper Clippings (1942-1968) and Travel and Events (1945-1950, 1967). Military includes documentation of Mr. Mathews' numerous military awards and citations, extensive travels, meetings with notable individuals and military and civilian leaders, speeches, writings, and memorabilia. Newspaper Clippings document Mr. Mathews' prolific writing career as a journalist, most notably as editor and publisher of the Arizona Daily Star and his extensive travels. The writings of other journalists on particular topics of interest to Mr. Mathews are also documented in this subseries. Travel and Events document Mr. Mathews’ extensive travels and special events held in his honor. Arrangement is alphabetical.
  - Military, 1923-1968, Subseries 1:
    - General Pershing's Funeral, 1948-1968 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Military and Professional Awards, 1923-1966 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - World War I; Awards and Photographs. undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - World War I; Photographs and Clippings. 1917-1919 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - World War II; Europe, 1916-1942 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1942-1965, Subseries 2:
    - Cuban Revolution, Africa, Alaska and Antarctica Trips, 1958-1961 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Dutch Indonesia, Orient and Korea Trips; Public Service. 1948-1950 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - European Trip; Public Service. 1966-1968 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Mathews Newspaper Cartoon, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Near East, Germany, Venezuela and Viet Nam Trips; Public Service. 1962-1965 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Other Writers, 1951-1953 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Soviet Union Trip, 1945-1951 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - World War II; Atomic Bomb, England and Near East Trips, 1942-1947 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Travel and Events, 1945-1950, 1967, Subseries 3:
    - 500 Arizonans Honor Star's Editor at Banquet, 1966 (Box 15a)
    - The Bikini 'A' Bomb Test; Aboard the USS Appalachian, 1946 (Box 15a)
    - From London to Toyko, 1945 (Box 15a)
    - Letters from the Pacific and the Third Fleet, Summer 1945 (Box 15a)
    - General Lemuel C. Shepherd Jr. Visit, May 1967 (Box 15a)
    - Korea, the 38th parallel and Toyko, 1950 (Box 15a)
    - Letters from Europe and the Mediterranean, Summer 1947 (Box 15a)
    - Letters from Indonesia and the Pacific, Summer 1949 (Box 15a)
- William R. Mathews Family Papers, 1939-1966, Series IX:
  The William R. Mathews Family Papers document the correspondence of Mr. Mathews’ mother as well as correspondence regarding the potential publication of her handwritten autobiography. Also included are several writings regarding the Strong family including historical sketches and genealogical notes representing Mother Mathews’ family.
  - Correspondence: Mathews, William R. Re: publication of “Mother Mathews Life Story”, 1943-1966 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Mother Mathews, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - "Mother Mathews Life Story"; copy, circa 1965 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - "Mother Mathews Life Story"; Original draft, 1939 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Sketch of the Life of Robert T. Mathews, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - The Strong Family in Indiana, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Typed copies of Strong Family History, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - The Western Branch of the Strong Family by Clara Murray Mathews, 1943 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Betty B. Mathews Family Papers, 1870-1975, Series X:
  This series documents Bettty B. Mathews and the Boyers family through correspondence, journals and diaries. It also includes various papers relating to Betty B. Mathews, including hand copied medical research articles.
  - Betty B. Mathews Journal, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Betty B. Mathews Trips Journal, 1935-1937 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Butler University, 1972-1975 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Mathews, Betty B., 1971-1973 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Diary of Eva E. Boyers, 1927-1937 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Diary of Mrs. J.S. Boyers, 1890-1909 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - J.S. Boyers; Account of Experiences, 1870-1879 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Medical Research Materials, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - "Silent Influences"; James S. Boyers,M.D., circa 1900 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1949-1974, Series XI:
  This series consists of newspaper clippings collected by William R. Mathews and his wife Betty B. Mathews. Clippings and magazines relating to Watergate and Richard Nixon’s resignation as President of the United States are also represented in this series. These materials were collected by Betty B. Mathews after the death of William R. Mathews.
  - Arizona Daily Star, 1949-1953, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - National Newspapers, 1949-1962, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - NNixon Related Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Nixon Related Magazines, 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook of Nixon Related Political Cartoons, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Ledgers, 1916-undated, Series XII:
  This series consists of ledgers belonging to William R. Mathews during his undergraduate education at the University of Illinois. Accounts and receipts for dairy purchases are noted, along with the account name. Most accounts were held by University of Illinois fraternities and sororities.
  - Ledger, 1916 (Box 19)
  - Ledger, 1916 (Box 19)
  - Ledger, undated (Box 19)